this morning if you could say something
about the suitor if you had anything to
say well it's about 42 summer pada just
a short verse some year to nakiya
12:41 nazar and which is the noble
method which is properly seen by him the
noble disciple copper properly
penetrated with understanding here
householder a noble disciple attends
properly from the origin to this very
dependent origination when there is this
there is this when there isn't this
there isn't this the miss arises this
arises then it ceases this ceases noble
method is noble understanding so as the
word I said what not what matters not
what method is there it's the one where
he properly attendants so you can't do
but teaches our Father you can either
see it or not see it and usually petite
some part is translated as dependent
origination I suppose is a translation
it's fine but the problem is it it
carries on a view of of an explanatory
nature so it's like cause and effect
that's how people regard but it's an
pada oh this is the cause this is the
result this is the new cause this is a
new result but it isn't the way the
bullet is crowded it's a principle
whereby while this is present this is
the also the result of it so it's a
simultaneous presence so with the
presence of feeling there is presence of
craving in regard to that present
feeling it's not your craving is the
result of your feeling they're
simultaneously present to the same
extent not knowing how to attend that
not seeing a necessary condition that
presently in the
within your enduring craving that's how
you crave so at its ibadah it's not an
explanation of what happens to you it's
it's a it's a direct insight of how to
approve things that happen to you
liability to craving green diversion
delusion all these things so that's why
it's a noble method method of overcoming
suffering but that's what you said how
do you do it you noble disciple means
you need to arrive view and you do it by
properly attending so you are caught up
in craving you catch yourself full of
desire for whatever sense experience or
desire to get rid of something what is
the necessary basis for that desire can
you have desire without having craving
hang on or I desire such and such things
without craving those things can you
have that it's impossible so then any
form of desire doesn't matter the
specifics of your design requires
presently enduring craving attitude of
craving and you can stop there now you
can say okay so my desire is written my
craving you're not you know you're not
basically overcoming it you might have
acknowledged it which is a good first
step but that's that one overcome it so
then the Buddha said you attend further
what is another necessary basis within
craving necessary basis for craving
exactly so you must be feeling either
Pleasant must be feeling either
unpleasant or must be feeling either
neither pleasant or unpleasant so you
started with I want this so much that
you know I'm about to do unwholesome
things just to get it you don't do it
you practice sense restraint but the
desire is still there through that
desire you discern the necessity of
present enduring craving which is
basically the container of that desire
now through that present enduring
craving you discern a necessary basis of
present enduring feeling which is a
container for your craving and then
you start Welling attending properly to
the nature that there is a feeling have
you created it did you have said it no
you subtract it to it so it's not yours
even if you want to make it yours
you're only basically maintaining it is
yours through not seeing it that it is
in yours and through giving in
habitually towards the desire that's
already contained within the attitude of
craving so through giving into the
desire you maintain ignoring the nature
of the feeling which is that it can't be
yours because if you stop ignoring it
you see that it can't be yours craving
disappears and disappears by being
included within there is a feeling not
by you choosing to that pick it and
remove it so then when the craving
disappears it's all bad right
that's right Bueller well all of this
like if somebody has the right view
already all of this would be just
further development of their right view
but even if you don't have the right
view training yourself how to discern
craving within the desire how to discern
feeling within craving not before or
after notice result psychology zation or
explanation or I crave because I know
while you crave you discern present
enduring feeling so while you crave you
feel and it's the craving in regard to
feeling you cannot have craving second
longer is the feeling disappears but you
cannot feeling well you can have feeling
without craving but the only way to
understand that is through abandoning
the craving not like finding out how to
not crave on top of your craving so the
only way to abandon to to understand how
you can have feeling without craving is
to first through craving you disorder
necessary basis of feeling and then
abandon craving but fully understanding
the necessary basis that's exactly but
it's about nothing else with this as a
necessary basis
this is enduring engaging me making me
act making me feel all of these things
so that's oh there's so many different
variations of potential bother the
suitors sixty in fact it's twelve
factors eight factors sometimes some
permitted some included some
because they are the principal principal
of discerning the necessary basis for
another simultaneous enduring phenomenon
it's all an explanation it's not a it's
not it's not a linear sort of set of
visualizations you have to go through in
order to practice it nonetheless
discerning what is my present situation
is there sense desired in me no is their
absence of sense desiring me yes what is
the present feeling on account of that
is there any desire toward that feeling
so now I have a peaceful feeling neutral
feeling do I have desire to to sort of
want that feeling more in which case
well it's an angle neutral it's
unpleasant now you've got to the body
seeing the body and an external yeah
object can you can even can you even
can't even fathom can't even think
imagine in utter complete abstraction an
external object without the necessary
basis of your body so seen those two
those two well seeing basically the
right order of things seeing this within
this not this within that and that's the
difference in the impotence of garlic
when not seen then yeah your feelings
are result of your craving because
that's how you assume them they're not
but you don't know that they're not and
because of that the only reality you
know is the reality that yet you are
craving and all this that's why it's
like a vicious circle until you
understand that you're craving cannot
make a difference to the nature being
subjected to the feeling and that you're
craving can never step outside of the
feeling it requires feeling as a
necessary container for it to endure for
it to manifest
so you don't want to be doing reflecting
a bump but it's no bother
like on random things because it's
already subtle enough to be understood
she's gonna just make it more abstract
so you want to find practical side of it
practical is feeling freedom from it as
in freedom for craving in regard to it
which is freedom from suffering because
one who sees Saddam assist but this is
some part one is this but it's over
assess the Dhamma
so literally the entire Dhamma is in
that principle and why is it and why is
that principle so important so profound
because if you see that you're presently
enduring desire fully embedded in the
attitude of your craving for this
craving for this to not be craving for
this to be if you see all of that that
experience it in its entirety as fully
contained fully determined formed the
Sankara by the presently enduring
feeling that you've been subjected to
you haven't created it you realize the
utmost of your desires and cravings and
wills it's actually rooted in something
else not you and thus cannot be yours
even if you engage with it but by not
dwelling on that long enough you do will
develop the notion of I am my own my
like my own possessions my own feelings
my own desires and everything else is
the result of that but it's our way
wrong so you wanna start including it in
a bigger context context it yeah your
mind must be like might be feverish with
the desire for this particular object
peripheral to that is the necessity of
the attitude of trailing can you have
desire without craving for what you
desire no so you realize okay so
whenever there is a desire i no craving
is there I don't need to see it written
on the wall craving know I know
desires present exclaiming is here
desire is a symptom of the attitude of
craving one should become familiar with
that you take it step further by the
sanction same principle and that's what
women learn how to attend properly so instead
learn how to attend properly so instead
of attending at what craving is pushing
you towards you attended the necessary
basis for the push of the craving that
the only someone a seeker you attend to
the boon to the back to the origin of
this attitude that I have that I'm not
denying but I'm not engaging within
either that's what sensory strength comes first
that's what sensory strength comes first
then you get to understand and then you
just get to be drilling and drilling the
same understanding to the same way of
properly attending and that's the normal
method that's the novel method exactly
as concise as you can explain it it's
another section here in regard to the
body this is when there is external name
and matter there is body when there
isn't external name of matter isn't body
when external name of meta arises the
body arises when external many meta
ceases the body diseases so if you were
seeing that that you're not if you were
pretending that description that's the
noble method by seeing that necessity of
presently arisen experience the whole
being like in this case your body is
rooted in a phenomenon different than
your point of view different in you and
when I say root I mean simultaneously
rooted that's the important that's why
it's so hard to see because we we can
understand causation oh this is the
reason this is the the basis and this is
the result but it's hard to understand
like us simultaneously enduring presence
of two things determining each other if
you look at this one is determined by
this one if you look at that one is it
tell me by the other one so the
termination is opposite from where you
look and that's the similarly the Buddha
games like two sticks holding each other
you remove one the other one cannot
remain so it's not one stick comes first
then the other one follows it's the two
sticks determine two that is not a cause
and effect it's not no it's whatever is
present here isn't within that you also
discerned presently enduring basis for
it
and you can't have that basis without
this thing being there how without you
be discerning discerning oh my craving
has been determined like my craving to
get rid of this has been determined by
an unpleasant feeling that all seniors
how would you decide that if you haven't
discerned the craving to get rid of this
first so you get to arrive at the
determination the necessary base is the
necessary container on account to the
presently arisen from under you became
mindful of properly as in you haven't
given in to it by default you haven't
acted out of it you became aware of its
own endurance and you were not a
bitterly trying to get rid of it I was
doing this I was doing something yeah
trimming is bad but you time to get a
little craving cannot be rooted in
anything other than craving that's you
try to get through the craving keeps
perpetuating the crave to let you need
craving craving for freedom you need
something yeah you need craving for
freedom like as a start-up for your
practice that can then eventually get
you closer to learning how to attend to
it properly so you actually free
yourself from craving without craving it
and this is how you do it as I was
describing it yeah you have to want to
crave the freedom from suffering which
is another craving and you suffer on
account of it but because of that
suffering on account of craving to be
free from suffering you will keep
looking for the way out of suffering you
will keep reading the sutras you will
keep practicing you will keep reflecting
to keep you will be keeping the presense
and all that is actually bringing you
closer to be free from suffering
bringing you closer to the stand the
craving and the Buddha said that craving
is to be abandoned by the means of
craving conceit is to be abandoned by
the means of conceit you here then
such-and-such became so the banner in
our house I hope he can do it I can do
it it's good to concede that thought but
because of that thought you actually
might get and start making the effort
stop taking it more seriously keeping
the precept more strictly all that and
because of that you will be
from considered she was your desire
consider desire did you wisely directed
against itself so to speak but in order
to do that you need to know what you're
supposed to do you know what the
practice is you can't just be randomly
denying affirming wanting not wanting
and then hoping that the results will
magically manifest only for
understanding of what the problem is you
get free yourself from problem so
suffering is a problem the most obvious
problem because it's felt unpleasantly
okay so now understand it now just not
feel it but understand it freedom from
suffering doesn't mean you never feel
unpleasantly means you don't come you
don't suffer on account of the
unpleasant feeling so and that's that's
achieved not but not feeling anything
isn't no feeling manifested but it's
manifested through understanding
whatever smile whatever feeling is there
because if you understand the
characteristics of the feeling as we
just started this talk you will be
unable to create it and there is no
claim there's not feel this world is not
suffering
it was so
you know it's a one who sees mindfulness
of the body sees deathless
the deathless one but what but
mindfulness of the body means
understanding of the nature of the body
when you say body my body
whatever that designation refers to you
have understood it through that
understanding that is how you partake in
deathless that ebon as in dispassion
absence impossibility to crave see the
deathless yeah you can't like see the
decklist you partake in it to understand
it yet
but as I said all these things that you
experience in your day-to-day now you're
not craving if you properly attend to it
will be pertaining to deathless as in
absence of this is what presence of
Nirvana is absence of craving absent
sooo craving so to the extent that
you're claiming is absent to that extent
the banished present if you're craving
had been fully uprooted the banner has
been fully developed it's automatic
but only through understanding the
natural craving not through following
blind method technique or something that
we just be doing and then somehow you're
craving is magically diminishing you
you're craving diminishes when you
understand what diminishing of craving
is so if so when you free for craving is
it's two pistols simultaneous presence
yes
the differences but this about is not
presence of the principle or not
principle is always there with this this
is that's how things work but the with
ignorance but it's of others refer to be
as with the grain so with feeling
craving is with craving your desire with
desire you have fighting and protecting
and losing and suffering in all these
things without feeling as in without
feeling being appropriate in his mind
with feeling that's fully understood in
its nature that cannot be owned there is
no claim without craving
so with this cup with this container
present this is present within it with
the absence of a container this is
absent within it but a principle of that
determination remains the same so the
principle could you could the person say
what would you say if someone said
that's that the principle is the what is
behind that principle what is the
ultimate ground where's the ultimate the
two sticks holding each other yeah this
is something beyond see the principle
you cannot make principle into one thing
yeah so but if you say what is the
ultimate behind this principle means
what I described as a principle of two
simultaneous things you regarding is one
and now trying to determine what's
behind it whatever it is that's what the
principle is the relationship of these
two things simultaneously present
because even if you think there is this
one ultimate ground
well yeah you tell me Danny exactly you
how can you know the ultimate ground
without thinking it which means that
thought is already secondary basically
to whatever you feeling whatever you
create you've user whatever your attention is
you've user whatever your attention is
so the only way to discern the principle
correctly is to start including your way
of attending to things in it
as in you choosing to attend this is
already within the principle so you
can't just leave your attention out and
then discern the principle because that
becomes explanation that becomes
psychology zation and that's why it's
not but it's a register further as far
as the person can see that principle you
can't see you can't step outside of it
that's what we keep talking about
peripheral awareness and practicing mind
fluency not like a mindful mindful but
read kunas your situation see whatever
you are attending but keep a corner of
your on the background as enough how
you're feeling where the currently moved
in use because that is what's directing
your attention like if you run if you
are unmindful like if you if you haven't
recollected the right context of that
craving is bad for example the craving
results in suffering if you don't have
that context in your mind
enduring when craving is present you are
going down the rabbit hole of your
desire for whatever he wants so your
attention is fully sent and directed and
thrown but that lack of understanding of
the context of craving if you do
maintain the context that craving it
should be unwanted because it always
means pain presence of credit means
presence of suffering does craving mean
suffering desire is suffering in itself
that's why you give into it to try to
get rid of it you maintain that context
ah so now you are all you are aware so
you are attending to what presently stay
but present state of mind and your such
as state of sensual desire or state
available but that attention is not
going all the way because you are
mindful of the context that sort of is a
necessary container for it so you're
already even unknowingly to that extent
certain in the beginning you're
practicing the principle participant
rightly you're going against the grain
well there is wanting but you are now
aware of the con
that it's a necessary basis for your
wanting and the only way you can arrival
it is to first restrain the actions that
are routed anything the actions that
come out as a result of your ones that's
way sila virtue sense restraint is a
necessary basis it must be developed
beforehand habit of no I will not engage
with sensuality no I'm not engage in
your world in gossip in malicious speech
in slander and all these things you
don't know why but you take it on trust
that you won't do it because you haven't
been doing it you're training yourself
to not automatically act unpleasant
nervousness desire by not acting
automatically immediately faces force
yourself to see the context of it by
acting automatically you mmediately jump
down the rabbit hole and you don't see
any context tree gets narrow and narrow
and that's exactly what's and
sensualities in your world it is
complete loss of perspective this is
non-duality see that that's the ultimate
non-jew but is somebody who says it's
duality of course the only way you can
how can you like see how can you be
aware of non-duality because your
awareness is already different from that
non duality which means there are two
things but you're just not ignoring one
you're ignoring your point of view
you're ignoring your perspective you're
ignoring your own awareness of the thing
that has a reason even if that's the
ultimate reality of non-duality yeah but
you're worried does it do oh but if you
were to see that whatever is the object
of my attention including non duality
the ultimate Nibbana means attention and
object or it can attend it if the object
is if I haven't been subjected to the
object no would I know the object if I'm
not attending no thus two sticks
determine each other depending on where
we look and there was never extended up
the point to get your attention to
attend to the origin or something of
itself that's inconceivable
you want to understand the background of
what you'll attend
that's what it went where the
determination of your attention is so
you're attending on duality what is the
background of it well it's it's certain
it's certain desire isn't it of towards
pleasure towards the ideal of ultimate
peace of non duality and merging with a
greater universe reality whatever you
want to call it it's motivated by that
that's present those are your intentions
they'll make you think about non duality
they are clearly fully ignoring by over
committing to the reality of non duality
which is again how can you know it
unless you can think it how can you
think it without attending it if you're
attending something your attention is
not it so beyond the true non duality
then even from that ideal of non-duality
would be complete unawareness of
anything will be complete non-existence
because it soon is you aware of
something to that extent
there is a difference so then you say oh
it's non-existent how can you think
non-existence because your thought is
existing so you're thinking
non-existence by existing it it's a
contradiction in terms
yet here you are maintaining the
attitude that when you think
non-existence when you think non-duality
when you think the ultimate reality that
is what ultimately it is yeah it's only
your thoughts cannot be anything
different than that so that's why we
never the never the issue is never find
in the reality hidden behind or running
into some new astral astral projected
round off of non suffering no it's just
literally stop this conceiving things is
yours to wrongly attending to them what
things your feelings your intentions
your perceptions that's it your mind
that's that this the ultimate that's
that suited when the Buddha says he
looks for croup who can he respect in
the world higher than him sorry okay
nobody but then he says why don't I
respect it up respect the Dhamma the
principle that he discerned it made him
the Buddha and so he he dwelt respecting
that they're seeing that yeah because if
that principle if things were not
actually like this as in if you were not
subjected to a feeling first as a
necessary enduring container for your
craving in regard to it for your actions
for whatever else you have on top of it
you wouldn't be able to feel so from it
the feeling would truly be yours you
would be its creator its owner its
manifest but you know you ignore the
fact that you're not and that's where
you think you are you stop ignoring it
you will stop thinking you are the
master of it but as I said you have to
reverse the order so now the only
feeling you know is the feeling through
your craving so when I first decided is
craving there as in leaning towards
leaning against attitude oh yes attitude
of no no I must get rid of it no I must
discern the feeling within this attitude
and then that feeling will be seen as
actually necessary basis for this
attitude and that's how a man gets sugar
craving that I was once a friend and if
ever not possible to do you would have
done it so that's what I said
so why don't I then respect the fact it
was possible to do it as in the
universal principle